Guide to the Marion Belanger, Rift/Fault
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Rift/Fault
2006-2015
WA Photos Folio 173
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.17
(2 boxes)
Photographs created by Marion Belanger, 2006-2012 and printed 2015 that document tectonic shifting of the North American Plate in California and Iceland.
Belanger, Marion, 1957-
Scope and Contents
Photographs created by Marion Belanger, 2006-2012 and printed 2015 that document tectonic shifting of the North American Plate in California and Iceland. Images in the "Rift" component document the rising eastern edge of the North American Continental Plate where it meets the Eurasian Plate along the Mid-Atlantic Rift in Iceland and include views of geothermal energy projects and the built environment. Images in the "Fault" component represents the subsiding western edge of the North American Plate along the San Andreas Fault in California and depict the built environment adjacent to the fault.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Radius Books on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2016.
Arrangement
Arranged under headings for Rift, Fault, and Ancillary Material.
Marion Belanger (born 1957)
Marion Belanger, Yale MFA 1990, is a photographer. Her work focuses on the cultural landscape, particularly where geology and the built environment intersect.
Conditions Governing Access
The Marion Belanger Photographs are the physical property of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University. Literary rights, including copyright, belong to the authors or their legal heirs and assigns. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Faults (Geology) -- California -- Pictorial works; Plate tectonics -- California -- Pictorial works; Plate tectonics -- Iceland -- Pictorial works; Rifts (Geology) -- Iceland -- Pictorial works; California -- Pictorial works; Iceland -- Pictorial works; Inkjet prints; Photographic prints; Radius Books; Belanger, Marion, 1957-
- Rift/Fault, 2006–2015
  Scope and Contents
  Views of sites along edges of the North American Plate including the Mid-Atlantic Rift in Iceland and San Andreas Fault in California created in 2006 and printed in 2015-2016 as ink jet prints, 12.875 x 16.375 inches (32.7 x 41.6 centimeters). The prints comprise an edition numbered one of five. Ancillary material includes a box with a mounted inkjet print, a signed title page, and interleaving paper.
  Arrangement
  Organized under three headings for Rift, Fault, and Ancillary Material.
  - Rift
    - Rift #1, image printed in 2015; image created in 2006 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 1)
    - Rift #11, image printed in 2015; image created in 2006 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 2)
    - Rift #22, image printed in 2015; image created in 2006 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 3)
    - Rift #23, image printed in 2015; image created in 2006 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 4)
    - Rift #26, image printed in 2015; image created in 2007 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 5)
    - Rift #31, image printed in 2015; image created in 2007 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 6)
    - Rift #43, image printed in 2015; image created in 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 7)
    - Rift #62, image printed in 2015; image created in 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 8)
  - Fault
    - Fault #10, image printed in 2015; image created in 2008 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 9)
    - Fault #18, image printed in 2015; image created in 2009 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 10)
    - Fault #23, image printed in 2015; image created in 2012 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 11)
    - Fault #26, image printed in 2015; image created in 2012 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 12)
    - Fault #28, image printed in 2015; image created in 2012 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 13)
    - Fault #30, image printed in 2015; image created in 2012 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 14)
    - Fault #37, image printed in 2015; image created in 2012 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 15)
    - Fault #52, image printed in 2015; image created in 2012 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 16)
  - Ancillary Material
    - Title Sheet, 2015 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 17)
    - Interleaving sheets, undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 18)
    - Box, 2015 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 19)
      Inkjet print mounted on box cover depicts a composite of Rift # 11 and Fault #27